JOHAN VAN DER MOLEN MORIS



 ♥ Edificio Rolando Chuaqui Campus San Joaquín Avda. Vicuña Mackenna 4860 Santiago, Chile ☑ johan.vandermolen@uc.cl jvandermm@gmail.com

(mobile) +56 957505278

https://jvandermolen.com

I am an Adjunct Professor of Statistics at the Pontifical Catholic University of Chile. My research interests include Bayesian methods and Machine Learning techniques, especially for nonparametric and high-dimensional models, as well as their applications in molecular medicine and education.

EDUCATION

2015-2020 PhD Statistics – University of Edinburgh

PhD Statistics

School of Mathematics. School of Mathematics. College of Science & Engineering Thesis: *Bayesian Semiparametric estimation of densities with unknown support.*Supervisor: Dr. Natalia BOCHKINA

2014-2015 MSc Statistics & Operational Research – U. of Edinburgh

MSc Statistics and Operational Research First Class (Distinction) · School of Mathematics. College of Science & Engineering Thesis: Estimation of the lower support point of an unknown density.

Supervisor: Dr. Natalia BOCHKINA

2006-2011 Mathematical Engineering degree – University of Chile

Mathematical Engineering First Class Honours · Faculty of Physical and Mathematical Sciences Thesis: Educational Data Mining: Prediction models for elementary schools students' performance.

Supervisors: Dr. Roberto Araya, Dr. Raúl Gormaz & Dr. Jaime San Martín

BSc Engineering Sciences in Mathematics 2006-2010 BSc Engineering Sciences in Mathematics – U. of Chile Second Class Honours · Faculty of Physical and Mathematical Sciences.

EMPLOYMENT

2024- Adjunct Professor – Pontifical Catholic University of Chile

Adjunct Professor, Pontifical Catholic U. of Chile Research and teaching position at the Department of Statistics in the Faculty of Mathematics. Teaching "Bayesian Methods" and "Probability and Statistics".

2021-2023 MRC Postdoctoral Fellow – MRC Biostatistics Unit, University of Cambridge

MRC Postdoc, U. of Cambridge Working with Dr. Paul Kirk on the development and refinement of Bayesian models that combine multiple omics datasets, with the aim of identifying patient subgroups and disease subtypes that are both reproducible and clinically actionable.

2021-2023 Lecturer, Demonstrator and Group Supervisor – MRC BIOSTATISTICS UNIT, UNIVERSITY OF CAMBRIDGE

Lecturer and Tutor, U. of Cambridge Lecturer (Cluster Analysis) and Demonstrator (Cluster Analysis and Multi-state Models) in the module "Advanced Biostatistics for Health Data Science"; group supervisor of 3 students in the MPhil programme in Population Health Sciences. Lecturer of "Bayesian Nonparametrics in Molecular Medicine" in the module "Statistics in Medical Practice" in the Part III MASt/MMath programme.

2020 Teaching Assistant – University of Chile

Teaching Assistant, U. of Chile (Sep-Dec) Teaching Assistant of the course "Experimentation and Modelling approach to Mathematics Cognition and Education". Working remotely, I have participated in the design of the course and delivered online lectures covering statistical topics such as Random Effects and Multilevel modelling, and an introduction to machine learning methods. I also covered applications using programming languages R and Python.

2016-2019 Tutor – University of Edinburgh

Tutor, U. of Edinburgh Tutor of Nonparametric Regression, Multivariate Data Analysis, Linear Statistical Modelling, Statistics 2 (including summer course), Statistical Methodology, Credit Scoring, Methodology Modelling and Consulting Skills, Engineering Mathematics.

2013-2014 Assistant Researcher – Center for Advanced Research in Education, University of Chile

Assistant Researcher, U. of Chile Development of automatic speech recognition models. Application of machine learning algorithms to identify content and teaching practices in classes. In collaboration with Prof. Bhiksha Raj and Prof. Rita Singh from Carnegie Mellon University. Project FONDEF D1111009. www.ciae.cl

Contact: Roberto Araya +56 2 978 2590 · roberto.araya@ciae.uchile.cl

2011 Internship – Center for Advanced Research in Education, University of Chile

Internship, U. of Chile (Jan) Study of prediction models of elementary school students' performance in an online exercising system.

Contact: Roberto Araya · +56 2 978 2590 · roberto.araya@ciae.uchile.cl

2009 Teaching Assistant – Pontifical Catholic University of Chile

Teaching Assistant Pontifical Catholic U. of Chile

(Mar-Jul) Teaching Assistant of Algebra (Year 1). Faculty of Mathematics.

2008-2009 Teaching Assistant – University of Chile

Teaching Assistant U. of Chile

Teaching Assistant of Linear Algebra (Year 1). Faculty of Physical and Mathematical Sciences.

PUBLICATIONS

Jul 2022 Bayesian nonparametric mixture inconsistency for the number of components: How worried should we be in practice?

Preprint

Submitted to Journal of Machine Learning Research. Available on arXiv:2207.14717. Authors: Yannis Chaumeny, Johan van der Molen Moris, Anthony C. Davison, Paul D.W. Kirk

Jul 2022 "Teacher, Can You Say It Again?" Improving Automatic Speech Recognition Performance over Classroom Environments with Limited Data

AIED 2022

Artificial Intelligence in Education. AIED 2022. Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Authors: Danner Schlotterbeck, Abelino Jiménez, Roberto Araya, Daniela Caballero, Pablo Uribe, Johan van der Molen Moris

May 2022 Unsupervised characterization of lessons according to temporal patterns of teacher talk via topic modeling

Neurocomputing

Neurocomputing.

Authors: Matías Altamirano, Pablo Uribe, Danner Schlotterbeck, Abelino Jiménez, Roberto Araya, Johan van der Molen Moris, Daniela Caballero

Nov 2021 Developing computational thinking teaching strategies to model pandemics and containment measures IJERPH International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health. Authors: Roberto Araya, Masami Isoda, Johan van der Molen Moris An Automatic Teacher Activity Recognition System based on Speech Transcriptions LACLO 2021 XVI Latin American Conference on Learning Technologies (LACLO) 2021. Authors: Pablo Uribe, Danner Schlotterbeck, Abelino Jiménez, Roberto Araya, Daniela Caballero, Johan van der Molen Moris TARTA: Teacher Activity Recognizer from Transcriptions Jun 2021 and Audio AIED 2021 Artificial Intelligence in Education. AIED 2021. Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Authors: Danner Schlotterbeck, Pablo Uribe, Abelino Jiménez, Roberto Araya, Johan van der Molen Moris, Daniela Caballero Sep 2020 Bayesian Semiparametric estimation of densities with unknown support PhD Thesis University of Edinburgh. Author: Johan van der Molen Moris. Supervisor Natalia Bochkina Mining Social Behavior in the Classroom 7th ICCCI 2015 Proceedings of 7th International Conference ICCCI 2015. Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Authors: Roberto Araya, Ragnar Behncke, Amitai Linker, Johan van der Molen Causal dependence among contents emerges from the collective online learning of students 5th ICCCI 2013 Proceedings of 5th International Conference ICCCI 2013. Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Authors: Roberto Araya, Johan van der Molen Impact of a blended ICT adoption model on Chilean Jul 2013 vulnerable schools correlates with amount of on online practice LT₄D @AIED Proceedings of LT4D Workshop @AIED 2013. Authors: Roberto Araya, Johan van der Molen 2013 ORAL PRESENTATIONS Mar 2023 OxCSML Seminar, University of Oxford OxCSML 2023 Invited talk. Department of Statistics, U. of Oxford, Oxford, UK. CMStatistics 2022, London Dic 2022 CMStatistics 2022 Talk in organised invited session "Advances in Bayesian factor analysis". King's College, London, UK. Nov 2022 Data Science and Statistics Seminar, U. of Essex Invited talk. U. of Essex, Colchester, UK. University of Essex Seminar Bayesian Nonparametrics 13, Puerto Varas BNP 13 Contributed talk at 13th International Conference on Bayesian Nonparametrics. Puerto Varas, Chile.

Mar 2022 CITIID Seminar, University of Cambridge

CITIID PhD and Talk at Phd and Postdoc seminar of the Cambridge Institute of Therapeutic Postdoc Seminar

Immunology and Infectious Disease (CITIID). U. of Cambridge, UK.

BSU-IEU Symposium, U. of Cambridge and U. of Bristol Oct 2021

BSU-IEU Symposium Talk at joint MRC Biostatistics Unit and Integrative Epidemiology Unit virtual

symposium. U. of Cambridge and U. of Bristol, UK.

Sept 2021 Bayes4Health, Cambridge

Bayes4Health 2021 Talk at postdoc away day of the Bayes4Health workshop. U. of Cambridge, UK.

HONOURS & AWARDS

2016-2019 Travel Grants for Poster Presentations

Travel Grants Several scholarships covering registration fees and travel or accommodation for poster

presentations at BNP12 (Oxford, 2019), ISBA(Edinburgh, 2018), BNP11(Paris, 2017),

CRiSM Master Class (Warwick, 2016).

2015-2019 Becas-Chile Scholarship for PhD Degrees

Becas-Chile Scholarship by CONICYT from Chilean Ministry of Education for PhD programmes. Scholarship

It covers tuition fees ($\approx £14,500$ per year) and living expenses ($\approx £1,400$ per month).

2014-2015 Becas-Chile Scholarship for Master's Degrees

Becas-Chile Scholarship by CONICYT from Chilean Ministry of Education for Master's studies. It Scholarship

covers tuition fees ($\approx £17,500$) and living expenses ($\approx £1,400$ per month).

2006-2008 Academic Excellence

Academic Honour award for academic excellence during undergraduate studies at University of

Excellence Chile.

> University of Chile Scholarship 2006

U. of Chile Academic Excellence Scholarship by U. of Chile that covers tuition fees for

Scholarship undergraduate studies.

OTHER INFORMATION

Computer Skills R, Python, LATEX, Julia, Matlab, Arena, Xpress.

Transferable Skills FOUNDER AND ORGANISER of Statistics PhD Discussion Group at U. of Edinburgh ·

Leader of Student Helpers at ISBA 2018 · Chair of session "Bernstein-von Mises

theorem: Recent results" at CMStatistics 2022.

Languages SPANISH (Mother Tongue), ENGLISH (7.5 IELTS test), GERMAN (Level A-2.1, Goethe

Institut), JAPANESE (basic level, Chilean-Japanese Institute of Culture).

Interests Bayesian Nonparametrics · Biostatistics · Machine Learning